this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
welcome listeners to new episode of
software engineering radio this time I'm
here in Amsterdam at the ppl conference
the practical product lines with the
emphasis on practical it's actually
quite nice conference and I promised
that to mark Doug Arnaud the organizer
that I'll mention the conference in the
podcast so he has some benefit from that
today's episode is a discussion about
well about product lines about complex
software about speed about time to
market and things like that with Yong
Bosch hello Yong hello Marcus how are
you today we're still a bit tired but
otherwise I'm fine and esperan helped me
this morning
and we're going to talk about various
things regarding complexity and speed
and and how to build large software and
variability and variants of software and
to understand we're well to understand
what we were going to talk about I think
it's very important to understand you're
young your background so why don't you
talk a little bit about who you are what
you do and where you come from and very
good to area now very good first of all
let me say that I'm very I'm honored to
be interviewed by you markers on
software engineering radio it's really a
pleasure to meet you again
I am currently VP of engineering process
at a company called Intuit intuitive I
think well known to our US listeners but
not so well-known for people in other
parts of the world necessarily I've been
there for two and a half years now
before that I was head of the software
architecture software applications and
technology laboratory at Nokia Research
Center in Helsinki Finland but I think
that some people that are listening to
this may know me from the time that I
worked as a professor of software
engineering in the Netherlands and in
Sweden where my main focuses were
software architecture and software
product lines and the reason that we are
both here at this conference is because
I think both you and I are giving and
have given keynotes at disk lessons this
time okay and your keynote is it's
titled basically what got us here won't
get us there which basically X
a change coming up or a change or that
already happened so it requires people
to rethink maybe some of what they have
been doing in the past so can you
correct characterize what you think
changes and what the thing is that we
need to do differently in the future
right
I believe the software engineering is at
an inflection point where traditionally
we have focused a lot on what I call
integration oriented software
engineering where the specifically the
integration stage but even a lot of the
work attitude at a development stage and
earlier has been very much focused on a
centralized heavily manual approach to
software engineering what I believe that
I increasingly see happen in Silicon
Valley where I live these days but also
in other places in the world is that
we're moving to something that I call
composition oriented software
engineering which focuses a lot more on
decentralized approach to software
development that have a much much higher
degree of automation with respect to the
way you bring the system together the
way the regression testing the way the
deployment of software etc and that's
what I try to cover in my keynote talk
yesterday that I believe that that is a
major transition that is taking place
right now and that software product
lines which is a topic of this
conference need to go through a need to
be deployed in a rather fundamentally
different much more compositional
fashion than what we've done in the past
and as a second trend that perhaps we
can touch upon later on become
increasingly prepared as the basis for a
software ecosystem where the platform in
the software product line isn't just
used internally in the company yes it is
also used outside again so it's
basically going from a closed world
assumption where you know all the
players all the stakeholders and also
all the products that are going to be
built with your product line you know
assets going to an open world assumption
where you basically say we're providing
some building blocks and we don't know
who they're who schools go lit up who is
going to use them and how yes that is
exactly where I think that we're going
if we look at almost every company that
has a launch successful product
line out there even though they are very
successful the amount of functionality
that is needed by these companies is
impossible to build all of all all
in-house so they are looking effect for
effective ways to partner with an
ecosystem of developers that helps them
develop the software that that they are
looking for and that has all kinds of
benefits it increases the stickiness of
your platform and off your product line
and the products in your product line
and it allows you to do a lot of
experience a Tavares that we couldn't do
if we would only do this inside the
company and because of that I believe
that both for small developers as well
as for successful platform and product
line companies software ecosystems are
very very important so looking at it
from an architectural perspective how is
a software ecosystem different from a
product line we already mentioned this
open/close thing but what does this mean
concretely so it concretely means a
number of different things the first
thing that it means is that several of
the operating mechanisms that we
traditionally used inside and inside a
company that were very much assuming
centralized control centralized
coordination etc no longer work when you
have hundreds or thousands or perhaps
even more developers outside your
company working in an undirected fashion
they do whatever they want to do on top
of your platform and you can try to
influence them but you can't control
them to the same extent as you do inside
a company that has a lot of consequences
that means that teams can basically
release their software at any time they
want to release it and they teams are
self-directed so centralized road
mapping does not take place these teams
pick themselves what they want to build
on top of your platform it requires a
much simpler architecture yes that also
is much more focused on backward
compatibility and interface negotiation
to work out small mismatches between
interfaces it also means
rather than giving your customers a
completely pre-configured and
pre-integrated product
your customers will increasingly start
to compose their own products I mean the
simplest and example is perhaps an
iPhone with all the application on top
of it there are lots of other
application if you look at Facebook you
can see that the applications already
are deeper integrated into into the
product but I believe that for many
companies this is if that have a
successful product line they will in
time move to a suffer ecosystem that
requires a number of rather big changes
in the way that software gets developed
and also I guess in culture because you
you don't well the the people who have
formally been customers or users which
is you know just users this is going
they're going to become in some sense
peers because they might also contribute
to your ecosystem and thereby indirectly
to your revenue and also to the system
and the architecture and all the stuff
around it yeah now I I think I heard you
say two things there is a major cultural
change that needs to take place inside a
company one of the quotes that I heard
and used yesterday and I heard recently
is culture each strategy for breakfast
and I think that for many situations
it's easy to formulate a software
ecosystem strategy for a company it's
much harder to drive the accompanying
cultural change that is needed in order
for that to be successful yeah so that's
the first aspect the other aspect is
what I have seen both of my time at
Intuit and at my time at Nokia is that
focus on the customer working in a
customer centric fashion is absolutely
crucial for success it has defined a
major part of the success for Nokia
being extremely customer forward it has
been almost all of the success or into
it and I think that we're going to
increasingly see this with many
companies going forward as we take our
customers much more serious do not treat
them as which would treat little
children there but view them as peers
and as Co innovators yeah so just to
make this clear if I understand you
correctly
then you're not saying the following you
continue in your company as you did in
the past and then you have a bunch of
api's that your peers slash users slash
ecosystem guys use what you're
suggesting is kind of that the internal
way of developing systems kind of
reflects the ecosystem approach so you
do it internally the way you would build
use the term mashups outside yes I think
that one of the things that I stressed a
lot in my talk yesterday is that speed
is the critical differentiator in
software engineering going forward and I
use the example of a company that
releases fifty seven times per day in my
mi talk which i think is rather
unrealistic for most most organizations
that requires for being able to operate
on such a speed requires that you work
at a highly decoupled compositional
fashion both inside and outside the
company and what I believe is that the
mechanisms that you need to effectively
work with external developers people
developers in your ecosystem the same
interaction mechanisms you can apply
inside your organization creating a good
separation between the people that
release and develop the platform and the
people that build the products or
additional chunks of product specific
functionality on top of the platform
so I think you're very correctly
identified that indeed the mechanisms
that you normally traditionally would
only have used in the interaction
between the company and the outside
world you're trying to pull into the
company and try to use them as
mechanisms to decouple development and
development teams I a little while ago
actually I think it was a couple of
years ago I did an episode with Donna
Fogle's from Amazon right and he told me
that the various teams who develop
certain features or let's say services
within the Amazon platform do that from
bottom to top they they specify
requirements they come up with the
architecture they do the implementation
so it's a much more vertical integration
and they also have very small teams and
I think this is necessary to be agile in
the
fancy of you you're proclaiming yes I
think that that's a very good viewpoint
I must say that also yesterday I
mentioned a number of the things that we
have learned from Amazon in my talk so
one of the rules that I'd really like
around Amazon it's a two Pizza rule
which basically says that no team can be
larger than what you can feed with two
pizzas if they are really really hungry
another one which is more architecture
related is the three API rule which says
that no team should have to bother about
more than three api's because if you
need to bother about more than three
api's you get into a situation in which
the architecture is simply too complex
for two small teams to move aggressively
there are two ways however to organize
software development and I'm still of
two of two minds which one is better you
can have component teams where a team is
responsible for a component and
basically evolves that component either
through centralized route mapping a
requirements management or in a much
more bottom-up let's we we will decide
how to evolve our component and then you
have the notion of feature teams and I
know that for instance eBay and I think
from description that you just gave also
Amazon work with feature teams yeah
the advantage of a feature team is that
it provides much more an integrated
focus on the different on one feature
top to bottom throughout the
architecture the challenge I believe is
that it is harder to integrate all the
different features during
release time and eBay for instance has
from what I've understood a biweekly
release in which during 48 hours all the
feature teams basically integrate their
code into a into the release code line
which is sometimes a very complicated
process the other aspect of that is that
I believe but I do not and this is a
belief this is not backed up by any
scientific evidence that the
architecture will most likely suffer
from more erosion more rapid erosion
when you have feature teams which could
be a disadvantage
bah however also component teams have
two disadvantages I was going to mention
that because on the one hand side you
read you're advocating decoupling and
decentralization and distribution of
responsibilities on the other hand if
you want to build a successful ecosystem
I think what you need is a a consistent
set of API is let's call it a consistent
architecture so that your peer developer
user ecosystem guys not to complicate it
so there is I think attention regarding
how much do you govern so things are
consistent at small and simple and
orthogonal and how much you give people
freedom so that they are flexible and
agile and and quickly to release right
the fact that we have decoupled
decentralized teams dozen three years
from the obligation to have an explicit
focus on the architecture that is not
necessarily something that the component
of feature teams should be concerned
about but there should be a team that
works hard at evolving the architecture
evolving it in such a way that it
maintains its simplicity but it is also
refactor to optimize it for the most
likely future extensions that are going
to come to the architecture that
requires of course that the architecture
evolves that means that we have two
standard processes as you for instance
see in the Java world where interfaces
get get deprecated it removes get added
you support different versions of
interfaces over time and that is
something that I believe requires the
needs to continue to be in place in
order to make sure that we have a
consistent architecture the most
important thing is that for most of the
work that any development team does they
only need to interact with the
documented and formalized interface that
the architecture provides and as little
as possible need to coordinate with
other teams in in their environment that
are working on order either other
features or on other components to the
launched extent possible since you're
emphasizing speed so much I guess there
is another consequence it basically
means that if you have to decide between
not releasing an API because it's not
yet perfect
yeah or releasing an API and then using
subsequent refactoring or incremental
improvement to make it nice then you
would probably opt for the letter so so
you get something out there so you stop
the echo system and then over time you
make it nice and provide maybe a new
version of the API that's cleaned up
perfection is the enemy of the good
it's my experience it's I say it's an
American saying but I think it's it's
true also in software development the
only way in which you can validate
whether you took the right design
decisions or not is by putting software
in the hands of customers either
customers as in end users or customers
as in ecosystem developers I believe
that that's the only way to validate
things and we have been I think too
reliant on our believes that we can
actually predict what customers or
external developers actually want in
practice that is just not true we have
to give it to them and ask them for
their opinion as they use it in practice
now many of the examples you've
mentioned eBay Amazon Google are web
applications right classical web 2.0
stuff right so I can very well imagine
how that works in this space also
releasing five times a day or ten times
a week or seven times a month is very
easy if you don't actually ship anything
if you do release now your company into
it as far as I know at least
traditionally has done shrink-wrapped
products you run in your PC how does
this I mean you can't ship a new box
every 10 hours you can't even require
your users to download and upgrade every
you know three times a day so how does
that play out are you moving away from
the shrink-wrap door so I counts in
detail describe our business strategy I
would hope this reason what I can say is
for many years already QuickBooks which
is one of our main shrink-wrap products
as well as by the way TurboTax when you
buy it on a CD whenever there is an
internet connection available and almost
all of our customers have internet
connections these days will download
what we call slip streams
in a traditional in the traditional
terminology which are basically upgrades
or replacement of specific components in
the in the product that allow us to
release new functionality or bug fixes
or other kinds of things so that's
becoming increasingly likely we are also
or increasingly possible we are using
that increasingly even in our
traditional products to almost sell a
empty box basically you get a a CD with
a license key and a very large chunk of
the functionality gets downloaded at the
moment that you install your software
rather than installed from the CD and
and we increasingly put downloadable or
online functionality to integrate well
into the product so we for this time
this year for the first time we actually
put an app store in our quick a product
which is a new kind of thing which
allows us not to only offer content
developed by into developers but
increasingly also functionality
developed by external developers and if
you go to intuit partner platform you
will see if you google for that you will
certainly find a link you will see the
opportunities that you have as an
external developer to build inside the
Intuit ecosystem that is millions or
tens of millions of users like you
worked for Nokia back then I don't know
how much you want to you know go back to
that world or what you're willing to say
but if you would still work for a Nakia
how would you do this in in more
embedded you know physical product
environments is this something that
applies there or yes so I must say and
this is perhaps my personal view on
career development or following one's
career I believe that many of the
innovations that we now see in the web
2.0 small startup Silicon Valley style
companies are techniques that over the
coming few years will come down to
to the embedded systems world as well
when in the time at Nakia and i don't
think that this is in any way shape or
form secrets is that we were and are
increasingly interested in over-the-air
updates which means that you can release
and push new functionality to a mobile
device after it has been bought by a
customer in the market in various forms
I mean you can do it through a PC
centric upload or you can do this by
real over-the-air Appler uploads in
areas where data changes are relatively
low I believe that since more and more
embedded systems are becoming networked
it becomes more a more feasible to drive
these kinds of models that we have been
describing here as well where even in a
better systems you can release
functionality basically continuously and
evolve the functionality of the embedded
systems however it of course requires an
architectural approach that protects the
do normally the part of the embedded
system that normally would need to be
certified yeah and also allows us to
approve to certification authorities etc
but that part of the system will never
be touched and cannot be brought down
through functionality that gets
downloaded on top of this embedded
system and I believe that this is a
direction that we will go to with cars
with consumer electronics with mobile
phones with all kinds of embedded
devices that we can see probably
starting on the industrial embedded
systems because the cost of goods is
relatively or the bill of materials is
not as sensitive as it is for
mass-market consumer products mm-hmm
so that kind of gives us a good
understanding of where you are and what
you're thinking is today let's go back
to to the let's say more classical
product lines approach which is kind of
closed and and very actually it's a very
managed approach a lot of things are
coordinated and big design up front
isn't doesn't have as bad a reputation
as everywhere else in that space now
that conflicts quite a bit with with
what you talked about
so let's let's look at a classical
approach of software product lines maybe
a short summary to three minutes and
then tie this back to what we discussed
last couple of minutes the first thing
which is very important to understand is
that software product lines should be
viewed in the scope of software use in
the broad sense and I hope that you
allow me to go elaborate a little bit on
this topic if you look back from the
1960s and they think 1968 was the first
conference around this the NATO
conference we see that we have two types
of reuse we have inter organizational
reuse the reuse of operating systems
databases graphical user interface etc
which has been extremely successful then
if we look at the internal
organizational reuse of modules
components etc we see that that has been
much less successful then and then all
the external reuse approaches so
software product lines proved to be the
first highly successful reuse approach
that was successful inside an
organization and if you look at all
kinds of companies ranging from Nokia
Siemens to Bosch to Intuit to Ericsson
etc all those companies were extremely
successful because they managed to link
a new business strategy to a a new
approach which will suffer product lines
and managed to grow their business or
run of their business units with an
order of magnitude or with an enormous
amount of success and that has been I
think a very the story behind software
product lines and why it has so received
so much attention so that's a
traditional software product line
approach which you see within a software
product line approaches typically that a
company goes through an evolution path
the first step is a company starting
from several product teams that are
developing products completely
independent of each other and do not
have any sharing whatsoever the next
step is often to start to standardize
the external components the info
on top of which you built your products
you standardized in the operating system
you standardized in a database on the
network protocols on the graphical user
interfaces on a webserver
whatever you need in your product but
you standardize on components that you
can get from the outside that only gets
you so far because your company is
leading in a particular domain and that
domain functionality you can't get from
anywhere the next step then is for many
companies to develop a platform a
platform is basically a layer of company
specific domain specific functionality
that all the products in the scope of
the product line need it's just the
platform it is not a product line in my
definition yet right because the next
step would be because the next step
would be what I call the software
product line which is a where D set of
shared components and the product line
architecture contain functionality that
is used by some or most but not all
products right and once you reach that
point software variability management
which has been one of the big research
topics for the last decade in software
product lines really becomes an issue
people because you need to decide which
thing goes into which product X and how
its configured may be exactly so you
have components that are either used in
some products and not in others and that
are configured differently based on
which product they are used in or in
which configuration of a product they
used there is however and this is
important to realize a subsequent
maturity step which I call the
configurable product base where there is
basically a code assent or a code base
from which through automated
configuration I can automatically derive
all the different products then I still
have variability management but it is it
is all automated there is no manual
management of variability anymore now
what you see is that in a stable domain
for a company that is successful in that
domain and spends a number of years on a
product line they will evolve to that
configure product base stage
for most markets and for most companies
they will stay in between a platform and
a suffer product line at brunch yeah now
there is a bit of a challenge with
suffer product lines to the extent that
we typically talk about sizable software
assets and if you continue to build them
with the integration oriented approach
that we started this interview with
typically the speed at which you can
execute tends to become lower so at some
companies if the platform release
frequency slips from six months to nine
months to twelve months to sometimes
even fifteen or eighteen months so you
have release cycles that are very very
slow with respect to the central
platform because of the size of the
software product line and the
complexities of managing all the
variability and all the dependencies
between the different assets which are
not managed automatically through the
architecture but I managed through
process and through manual activity yeah
there are some deviations of this but I
think in the interest of time there is
the notion of product populations that
Rob phenomena has been working on there
is the notion of program of product
lines for extremely large systems yeah
which but let's not go into that yeah
aspect right now so it gives it a little
bit of a context of the traditional
product line approach you're saying and
then the ecosystem comes in as a next
step after the product line where you
allow external folks to contribute to
products in the sense of the product
line yes that is exactly how I think
about it the way that I think about it
is that going from a system or product
specific way of working to a software
product line is typically driven by
company driven a company driven
variability a company has many similar
products and wants to exploit the
commonality between those products while
managing the variability in Suffern
ecosystems the transition from Suffern
product lines to suffer ecosystems is
often driven by customer needs or
customer desired variability customers
want to have much more configurability
much more function
analogy that they can use that the
company itself cannot provide and then
what you see is that companies feel a
push towards opening up that platform
providing it to external developers to
help have other companies help them
satisfy customer needs and this is not
just help this also has a number of
other quite significant advantages and
then obviously it needs to be
composition oriented as opposed to let's
say feature um feature model selection
kind of stuff because there isn't the
whole thing from which you select
exactly now I think earlier in the in
this conversation you mentioned the
notion of a closed world to such exactly
things we cannot use a closed world
assumption in this case especially in
when you have an undirected ecosystems
or where the developers do not get
specific instructions from you on what
to build but they can basically make it
up themselves they will always think of
things that you didn't think about from
the eginning yeah which is of course
what makes you successful in the end in
the end exactly because the way one way
to look at a software ecosystem is that
for the platform company it is a
relatively cost effective and fast way
to have a lot of innovation
experimentation take place with
customers and which you can and this is
where things become a little bit of a
tension point between external
developers and the platform a product
line company you can you can incorporate
successful innovations into the platform
when they prove to be successful the way
things often happen is you see a
multiple domain specific customer
specific editions being built on top of
your platform when you as a product line
a platform company see that there are
multiple out there and that the
customers really like them you know that
you have a piece of functionality that
you can go in platform ice and pull into
the platform in order to make your own
or make sure that your own platform
remains competitive now so in that sense
then you see that there are a lot of
experimentation took place you can take
the successful experiments and over time
incorporated me your platform and work
out financial reimbursement mechanisms
with the external developers and other
ways
in order to make sure there is a
continuous flow of new innovations
coming in it's probably also a good
recruiting tool you just hire the best
ecosystem guys into your company if you
look at some companies that have been
very successful in the upper operating
system platforms I mean one company
starts with an M I suppose they have a
history of buying the successful
companies that have built new innovative
functionality on top of their operating
system or they build themselves and then
out-compete everybody else but they have
actually had have a history of buying
companies that built valuable
functionality on top of of their
operating system just to pull their
functionality into the operating system
just to make the distinction clear this
is all this discussion is not about open
sourcing your product you're still a
commercial company your product is
basically still closed source except for
the API is of course so it has nothing
to do with this idea that's that's a
although for some of the processes and
approaches of community building are
relevant in both yes I think that there
is a parallel with the open source
software community but it is clearly not
the same as open source I mean we are
still looking at a platform or a core
set of functionality that has
significant value to its customers to
the point that they're willing to to
exchange what our CEO calls a value for
value so they're willing to pay us for
something that we that gives them a lot
of value in that picture the picture
that we're now looking at it
unfortunately the people on the radio
cannot see are two areas where open
source actually plays a role at the
bottom layers of the stack where
functionality is highly commoditized
yeah we may either put solutions in the
open source domain in order to share the
maintenance cost of infrastructure with
other players in the industry the other
technique that we are are using is to
put small open source seed applications
in the ecosystem as a starting point
to help others external developers to
get going in new domains where they
possibly wouldn't have either entered
directly or not have entered in the same
way as we would have done however in
that place the license terms are often
on the Saffir are typically different
because we do want to have the
opportunity to ones that functionality
which is very early in the indie
adoption curve maintained receives
mainstream adoption we want to be able
to pull that functionality into our
platform and we then don't want to be
constrained by the open source license
approach that that we would perhaps have
in a highly commoditized suffer so to
summarize there are parallels with open
source communities I mean we have
community building etc but and we do use
open source in our ecosystem approach
but it is not equivalent to writing
source software approach now there is
one thing that that I find interesting
if you if you want people to to
contribute to your to your systems and
to your applications then I guess you
have to make it as easy for them as
possible in the sense that you can't
necessarily ship them your whole
whatever big fat server based platform
you have to maybe even componentize your
platforms where people have you know can
pick apart and and and start with a very
small environment so what's the
consequence for the platform for the
basis of your applications using that
approach is there a consequence or there
there is your experience there there is
definitely a consequence but one of the
ways that that we work with this is that
we offer a hosting environment for
external developers as well as surface
API so that they can access so they
don't need to download and create a
local copy of a very large and
complicated infrastructure that wouldn't
be real anyway because there wouldn't be
any customer data to experiment with etc
etc so rather than ask
external developers to install our copy
of the infrastructure on their
environment we suggest that both for
prototyping and testing and for
deployment purposes they use our our in
our infrastructure but we do offer and
this is how we do it at Intuit I mean
there are other companies that take
different approaches we do offer
federated approaches as well in which
you can host your solution in your own
infrastructure but you can feather it in
through web services into our our
infrastructure yeah so in your case
you're actually so again going back to
the traditional shrink-wrap quicken and
stuff that was basically a desktop
product right has this evolved to your
web-based application service providing
kind of thing or is this a new platform
a new environment we are actively moving
all functionality that we have been
providing on the desktop enormous on a
CD traditionally to online as well that
doesn't mean that we drop our desktop
products and again now we get into
business strategy and I'm I'm not the
right person to talk about that but we
are moving the same functionality or new
functionality that makes more sense in
an online or in a mobile context to the
web and we actively work where we can to
make sure that you have access to your
data independent of where you are on
your desktop whether you are on the web
or where do you honor you on your mobile
device or independent of location so
that we try to separate data from the
exact deployment infrastructure in which
you're you're using things so you have
you basically ubiquitous access to all
your data all there's also an
interesting architectural challenge to
build functionality in a way that it can
be used on the server in a very scalable
environment right on a desktop and maybe
even on the phone yes with the selection
of the programming language I guess
there is a lot of decisions that need to
be taken in that context but of course
it's it's clear that the more the more
read restricted the resources that you
have on the on the device that is with
the customer at that time
the more you only DUI on the device and
most of the computing and in the server
background but I believe and it was a
bit of doubt where where the industry
would go I think a number of years ago
but it's clear that customers want their
data to be secured and stored in one
place and and and maintained from a
privacy perspective but they want to
have access from it to it from wherever
they basically are and I think that
that's not just something for the web
2.0 world over time you will see exactly
the same in the embedded systems world
where you can basically access your car
from wherever you are not just from
sitting in your car net which is I think
a new development that many a metal
systems companies haven't really spent
too much time thinking about so
basically what you said is that you
you're building a new platform in
addition to the existing shrink-wrapped
platform against one of the challenges
is that the new platform initially
requires a lot of investment and doesn't
create a money so how do you how do you
convince your you said you're not the
right person to talk about business so I
guess you're there is somebody you need
to convince the guy who talks about
business how do you do this yeah I think
that's that's a really good question and
not necessarily a very trivial one to
answer the first myth that I would like
to take I would like to address here is
that many people believe that embarking
on a software product line approach
requires a major upfront investment I do
not believe that that is actually the
case I think we can do get going on a
product line initiative against a
relatively lower effort there is however
a second myth and that's what I've seen
that many of the companies that I've
worked with or for in the past and that
is that people believe that a new
platform will replace will be the model
of all platforms and replace all the all
the existing platforms Dennis has in my
experience never been the case once
there is a platform or product line out
there that has revenue per hour
generating products out in the market
there's almost never a business reason
to actually retire that platform
what you do see is that over time
resources move from the existing
platforms to the new platforms so I have
a model in which I based on experience
with a number of companies and
introducing product lines where I
basically try to map out what I call for
adoption phases for going through a new
product line the first phase is what I
call the exploration phase Denner is the
initiation phase to build that face and
then the institutionalize phase okay so
I guess let's look at each of them
briefly absolutely so the the
exploration phase is where you probably
find out whether the new thing makes
sense yes that is exactly the the idea
it's often driven out of the product
development organization and based on a
frustration with some of the existing
platforms and trying to stretch them
into the new requirements that exists in
the organization now what you see is
that it's relatively relatively small
investment that takes place there there
is never any expectation to generate
revenue it's mostly around prototypes
and experimentation and there is a a
heavy technology focus there's not that
much of a link to the business strategy
at that point if you are a process
methods and tools person the focus that
you have in this case is that you start
to develop the vision and early design
of processes of tools of operating
mechanisms and you try to figure out ok
if we are going to work in this
fundamentally new fashion or an't
approach with this new platform what
would this look like and what is the
work that has a long lead time yeah that
assuming that this will work we should
initiate now and this can be SEM or test
automation deployment approach to
something like that so you develop a
vision of what it would take to be
successful here mm-hmm and then the the
initiation phase is probably broadening
the scope getting people interested I
mean real people real developers and
helping them get started yeah so between
the exploration phase in the initiation
phase decision right there is a decision
that takes place and this is one of the
things that is I believe very important
at this point there needs to be an
explicit link to the business strategy
so the house
be an agreement with the business side
of the house that there is a need for a
new platform that a new platform will
have a specific scope or focus within
the overall product portfolio of the
company and that it requires some level
of investment that is agreed upon
initially and then the idea is there is
a noticeable investment there are
resources being drained away from the
existing product lines and platforms and
and this is the hard part there is no
revenue which is really difficult there
is a little bit of upfront investment
that is necessary not as much as people
one often think that there is some work
that is needed at this point you should
also start developed the first offerings
and first products are first services so
the idea is that as rapidly as possible
do you get a first offering or product
or service out in the hands of customers
first in alpha or beta approach but as
much as possible in a revenue-generating
context my experience is that once you
generate revenue on top of a new
platform or a new product line it's much
much easy to make sure that you don't
get killed in the launch R&D yes I guess
you want to keep this phase for the
shorter the better i yesterday in my
keynote described it as you're a
beautiful little bird sitting in a swamp
full of poisonous snakes and everyone is
trying to is trying to kill you yeah now
there you get into the hardest part from
a process methods and tools perspective
because what you need to do is you need
to transition the staff that gets to
work on this new platform in a way that
they completely rethink in terms of
mindset process tools architecture etc
how they go about self development and
since these people most often are from
within the company I've been working on
the old platforms and product lines if
you do not give some explicit guidance
they will typically fall back in the old
ways of working yes and you will not see
half of the benefits or even none of the
benefits of this new platform initiative
a product line initiative so and
one of the things that I've tried in the
past which has been quite successful is
what we've called the immersion program
where during one or two weeks you take
new staff or staff that comes into this
new plant product line and educate them
to the largest extent possible or
explore approach brainwashes one
approach to think about this often not
as positively considered by engineers
and then after that once they get
working give them good support from a
coaching perspective so you can build a
core of a culture around this new
platform I think that that's very
important so at the end of the
initiation phase the first offerings
were in the market they typically on the
fringes of the product portfolio for for
the company because you don't want to
take too much risk and you are
generating revenue once you've reached
that stage you can't feel pretty good
about yourself to everything yeah and
then the political battles probably are
our reduced motivator because the people
understand the potential exactly and
then you're stepping into the build out
phase that's when you really start
believing in that that's your next way
of making money exactly and and the
importance here is to stress to everyone
in the company this is not focused on
taking away resources from the existing
or revenue generation from the existing
product you want to grow not to replace
exactly the idea is that the new product
line is growing the business so it's
creating new opportunities that we
couldn't realize with our existing
product lines and platforms so what you
then see is that the amount of resources
is increasing but also the revenue is
increasing which makes it often a lot
easier and the offerings are in them
there are already offerings in the
market but increasingly many offerings
are starting to touch the core of your
market so you start to complement your
existing product lines in your core
markets with new offerings or new
products or services based on this new
Suffern Suffern product line what you
see is that at this stage the core of
the business so the key business leaders
typically become heavily involved
because they won't see that there's
potential here they see that there is
revenue here there's growth opportunity
here and they want to be actively
involved and focused on this
what you then see is that over time
there will be a shift of resources from
the old product lines and platforms to
the new product line but that's only
natural it basically means that the old
platforms are mature I've basically in
the cash cow stage so what you want to
do is to generate as much revenue from
them and basically shift investment to
the to the old one from a process
methods and tools perspective you then
really focus on driving scalability
safeguarding architectural integrity
it's very easy to have a very high level
of architectural erosion in this state
so you need to have selected refactoring
efforts that gets invested in and this
is often also where variability
management becomes a real issue yeah I
think that the key message to the to the
to the people in the old platform is
that you don't actively kill it but you
have something new that you can move to
once the old platform naturally fizzles
out yes I guess that's the that's the
way maybe to talk more related and the
idea is that the old platform often for
the old platform to fizzle out as you
described it often takes many years
sometimes even decades there at the
amount of resources working on those all
platforms it tends to decrease quite
significantly all the time and I think
that's important so then the last phase
is the institutionalized phase yes this
is the new mainstream so then the
platform has become the new mainstream
as you said the investment has
stabilized you have high and growing
revenue and you have your next
generation offerings out in your core
markets and end in the growth areas that
you were focusing this on then people
don't talk about this being the new
platform anymore right it's just that's
it a current platform and then the focus
for process methods and tools focuses on
on process optimization on
institutionalizing the management of
commoditization of functionality because
then you need to become concerned about
not only what new functionality do you
take into the platform but also what
functionality do you actively push out
and replace with external components so
you are not spending resources on
juncture functionality that your
customers couldn't care less about I
mean that's not if anything that's
contextual for your organization you
should spend as little more Sun these
are the commodities exactly and then the
final is that you have to remain very
vigilant with respect to design erosion
for the architectural level so continue
to invest in architecture refactoring
efforts and the challenge is that if you
don't do that
over time typically in many product
lines the lifetime to product line can
be diminished quite significantly if you
do not keep it up to date to the current
needs of the organization I think that's
that's that was really interesting is
there anything else in that context that
you want to add for me the important
thing here is that it's important to
realize that are a number of phases that
run tollgates and that there are ways to
go from one stage to the next and make
sure that you do all the right things in
that stage what perhaps is important to
mention at this stage is then and again
if you go to to my personal website if
you google my name you will find it
actually will put this stuff into the
show notes so people don't even have to
Google well that's even better there are
are some presentations and some articles
that describe what I call the five
dimensions that you have to consider
during the adoption stages so that's how
do you select the functionality to build
how do you manage the architectural
harmonization once you bring in new
products into this new product line how
do you organize do you actually
formalize the organization or do you do
this as part of the existing product
teams how do you manage funding and how
do you scope the shared components and I
think that these five dimensions are
around fundamental in getting the
adoption of a software product line
approach right and then you'll see that
over time from the early success to the
increasing scope to increasing maturity
there are different decisions that you
have to take in these five in these five
dimensions that I that I describes and
for each of these dimensions and
depending on the stage where you are you
need to take a different approach based
on my experience with
all the companies that I've worked with
in the past Anders and I guess in
general introducing a new platform new
product line is introducing something
new and there is a lot of writings about
how you introduce new things into
organizations for example the book from
Linda rising and Maryland man's fearless
change so I guess taking some of these
things into account and I think we had
an episode that's tough that's why I'm
mentioning it it's probably also a
useful thing yeah it's very easy and
especially for researchers often it's
very easy to think about the strategy
and envisioning of how it could work
within an organization actually
achieving successful implementation in
an organization is infinitely much
harder yes and in Silicon Valley the
term is ideas are are a dime a dozen
basically it's all about execution and
that's where we are here as well the
execution of a successful software
product line introduction and adoption
is not trivial and you really benefit
from thinking very carefully on how to
do this and and where possible bringing
in some external expertise in order to
make sure that you do not fall into any
of the traps that other people have
already fallen into you and fall into a
new trap exactly there are still enough
new chips traps for you to fall into so
you're not too successful okay but as a
concluding remark I want to say that if
you look at all these companies that
have successfully adopted software
product lines in the past if you look at
Nokia if you look at the Philips if you
look at Bosch Ericsson HP talis in the
nel Talas navel into it and even small
and medium-sized companies when you are
successful with combining a snoo
business strategy with a successful
software product line introduction you
can grow your business tenfold the
rewards are enormous yeah and that's
what we shouldn't forget this is not
just a technology think this is
combining technology strategy and
business strategy and a very fundamental
and successful fashion just make this
clear you didn't in what we
just recorded and talked about you
didn't argue against product lines you
just said that product lines in this new
world have to take a little bit of a
different form yes what I'm concerned
about is that if you are not careful
about how you introduce our four product
lines
the traditional approach may very well
make you less agile and less fast and
the work that I'm currently looking at
is what I call compositional software
engineering is a dumped software product
lines but do it in such a way that you
do not slow anyone down instead you
allow people to accelerate even further
and if you focus on speed instead of on
efficiency I think you can combine
highly successful product lines with a
very rapid and agile introduction of new
products to the market ok very good
I think that that wraps it up thanks
very much John for being on the show as
we like to say very good thank you very
much for inviting me Marcus I had a
great time
ok thanks
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at s e - radio net or if you're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called
Vegas
[Music]